Thank you very much, Vincent.
多謝,Vincent.
Good morning, everyone.
Special good morning to all the mothers here today.
一個特別的問候向所有的母親。
I wish you a happy Mother's Day.
願你有一個快樂的母親節。
It's wonderful to be with you again.
很高興能夠再一次來到你們的當中。
And I thank Pastor Har for inviting me.
亦都多謝夏牧師來到邀請我。
When he invited me, I did not know the day that he invited me for was Mother's Day.
當他邀請我來講道的時候,我原本不知道這一天就是母親節。
Mother's Day is a difficult day to preach.
因為母親節是很難講道的一個日子。
Because it's a hard day for many women.
因為對很多的婦女來說是一個心痛的日子。
Many would like to be mothers and do not have children.
有很多人是想有小孩,但是沒有這樣的機會。
Others have had children who have passed away.
有些母親甚至有些兒子已經過世了。
Others have divisions in their families and are grieving over their separation from loved ones.
或者有些母親因為他們家庭的爭執的緣故,
是為了他們的家庭來傷痛。
And on Mother's Day, we often promote an idealized view of women.
很多時候我們講道的時候會常常提到一個很理想的母親是怎樣。
And that can be discouraging to women.
但是對於某些的婦女來說是一個反面的作用。
Because life is often far from perfect.
因為生命裡面是不是完美的。
This morning I do not want to present an idealized mother or a cardboard character to you.
今天我所講的信息不希望集中於一個理想的母親,
或者標榜一個母親是怎樣。
I will try to present a realistic picture of what it means to be a mother.
我希望來形容一個母親,一個真實的母親應該是怎樣。
We are going to study a woman whose life was not easy.
我們今天所查考的是一個不容易過的母親的生活。
And yet she found meaning in God.
但是她在基督裡面能夠找到她的意義。
And she was used by God in her home and in her nation.
她在她的家庭,在她的國家是被神所用。
The woman we are going to look at today is Hannah in the book of 1 Samuel.
今天我們所說的婦女在撒姆爾基上。
And we are going to see Hannah's trials, her trust, and her triumph.
我們看到Hannah這個人三方面,一個是她經歷的考驗,
她對神的信靠,和她得勝的經歷。
We are going to learn from Hannah that a godly woman
is a woman who triumphs over her trials by trusting in God.
我們會學習一個敬虔的婦人,
因為她的信靠在神的使領裡面能夠得勝。
So let's look at her story in 1 Samuel chapters 1 and 2.
我們今天所看的是撒姆爾基上第一章和第二章。
Hannah lived about the same time as the events in the book of Ruth.
Hannah她本身活著的時候大概是路加那本書的時代。
That was the time of the judges,
and it was a very dark time in Israel's history.
那時候是一個事實的時代,
也是以色列一個很黑暗的時期。
We read that she lived in the city of Ramah,
about five miles north of Jerusalem.
剛才我們閱讀的經文裡面,
我們知道她在拉瑪所飛的地方,
是在距離耶路撒冷大概是五里之遠。
She was married to a man named Elkanah.
她嫁了給一個人叫做以尼加拿。
He was apparently a prosperous man.
他可能是一個比較富有的人。
Because he has two wives and he seems to have a distinguished pedigree.
因為他有兩個老婆,
而且他的家族的族譜可以見到他是一個很好的家族出來的。
His other wife's name was Penina.
他另外一個太太叫做比利娜。
It's presumed that Hannah was his first wife.
Hannah本身可能是第一個的老婆。
Because she is named first.
因為她的名字是列在之前。
It may be that he married Penina because Hannah was barren.
他可能和比利娜結婚是因為Hannah沒有小孩。
And having children to continue his family line and inherit his land was very important.
在當時來說,能夠生育兒女,
能夠承受家產是一個很重要的事情。
The passage we read this morning describes Hannah's trials.
今日我們所看到的故事是講到Hannah所經歷的考驗。
Her trials are related to her barrenness.
她的考驗就是因為她不能夠生育兒女。
Our passage emphasizes that she had no children and that the Lord had closed her womb.
在我們所讀的經文裏面,我們看到她不能夠生育,因為神令她不能夠生育。
It also says that Penina, Elkanah's other wife, had children.
他亦都提到比利娜另有一個妻子有兒女。
Penina was Hannah's rival.
比利娜和Hannah是敵對的。
She used to provoke Hannah grievously and irritate her.
因為比利娜視上用找尋的機會來帶大,來激動她。
She did this because she had no children.
因為她沒有生育到任何的兒女。
Perhaps Penina reminded Hannah of passages like Deuteronomy 7, verses 13 through 14.
很可能比利娜利用生命記第七章所提到關於神的祝福。
That passage describes the Lord's blessing on people who obey Him and keep the covenant with Him.
那段經文提到神如何將福氣賜給所有信服祂的人。
It says the Lord will love you and bless you and multiply you.
在那段經文,生命記十三章提到神必愛你,賜福於你。
He will also bless the fruit of your womb and the fruit of your ground.
第十四節提到你的男女不能生育,生畜也不能生育。
And there shall not be male or female barren among you or among your livestock.
剛才提到神會賜福你所生產的男女和生畜都能生產。
So perhaps Penina reminded Hannah of this promise of blessing.
可能比利娜利用這個來向哈拿提醒神對他們的祝福。
And it's likely she suggested that Hannah had not been obedient to God.
可能她會說,哈拿你不來信服神,所以你有這樣的情況。
And therefore Hannah had been cursed by God with barrenness.
所以神會咒詛哈拿使她不能生育。
Elkanah's family worshipped the God of Israel.
伊利加拿這個家族是敬拜神。
And they went up to the tabernacle or central sanctuary for the main Jewish festivals.
所以每次他們都會去到會幕,就是那個聖所的中心來敬拜神。
Those were Passover and Pentecost and tabernacles.
重要的節日是包括如月節、五旬節和鑄鵬節。
These were times of joy when the Israelites would celebrate God's blessings on the year's crops.
在這個節日裏面,那些以色列人會很高興來歡樂和飲宴,
因為神賜福給他們地上的土產。
But these times of celebration must have been especially hard for Hannah because she was barren.
但是在慶祝的時候可能對哈拿來說是特別困難的時期,因為她是沒有子女。
The women would bring their children and they would talk of their homes and their family lives.
可能其他的婦女會將他們的子女帶過來,在那個時候他們一起講一些家事。
And Hannah would have no children to talk about or to show to the other women.
但是哈拿本身因為沒有子女,不能夠將她的子女帶到那些婦人當中
來跟他們分享。
At these festivals, the people would offer animal sacrifices to the Lord.
在那個節日裏面,那時候的人會將一些獻祭獻給神。
And the priest would then give them back some of the meat from the sacrifices to eat in a family meal.
但是那時候的祭司就說,當你獻上的東西,
他會將一部分所獻上的禮物歸還給奉獻的人。
And so Elkanah would then give the meat from the sacrifice to his family for them to eat.
所以以尼加拿作為一個家主,會將那些祭肉來分給他們的家人。
And he'd give a double portion to Hannah.
在這個情況底下,他將雙份來交給哈拿。
The Bible says he did this because he loved her, even though the Lord had closed her womb.
他這樣做是因為他愛哈拿,雖然是神令他不能夠生育。
He apparently wanted to assure her of his love and commitment to her.
可能他藉著這個方法來肯定他對哈拿的愛和承諾。
Even though the Lord had closed her womb.
雖然他是沒有任何的子女。
This act of love apparently caused Penina to become jealous of Hannah.
可能在這個情況底下,更加令到比尼拿更加來嫉妒哈拿。
And it caused Penina to reproach her about her lack of children.
特別是在這個時候,特別來到辱罵她,挑動她,因為她沒有子女。
And Penina's taunting and provoking of Hannah must have become very hurtful at these times.
在這個情況底下,可能比尼拿對哈拿帶來一個極大心裏面的傷痛。
Hannah would become so troubled that she would weep and she would not be able to eat.
甚至到了一個地步,不想哭和不想吃飯。
To Alcanna's credit, he would try to comfort Hannah when she was distressed.
以利格勒其實都不錯,在這個情況底下,他常常來安慰哈拿。
He said to her, "Hannah, why do you weep?"
他會問, "哈拿,為什麼你哭啊?"
"Why don't you eat?"
"為什麼你不吃飯啊?"
"Why is your heart sad?"
"為什麼你的心裏面這麼傷痛呢?"
"Am I not more to you than ten sons?"
"難道我不是比十個有十個兒子更加好嗎?"
I think his questions indicate he did not really understand her.
他的問題可以表示出,他並不完全明白一個女人的心理。
And like many husbands, he far overestimated his ability to keep his wife happy.
好像很多其他的丈夫,他高估自己能夠令到他的妻子高興。
He seems to be thinking, "Dear, you have me, what more could you want?"
親愛的,如果你有我之後,你還需要些什麼呢?
My wife often reminds me that I cannot make her happy.
我的太太也經常提醒我,我不能夠完全滿足她,讓她有快樂。
The Lord is the only one who can do that.
只有神才能夠滿足她。
Alcanna did not seem to realize this.
但是伊利加拿定不了解這件事情。
So Hannah has no other person who understands her.
所以Hannah是沒有一個人能夠了解她。
She has no friends she can go to for help, and she is all alone.
她沒有一個朋友她可以去訴苦,她是自己一個很孤單的個人。
Furthermore, she knows God is the Lord of hosts, as He is described in verse 3.
在第三節的時候,她提醒我,她明白神是一個萬君之神。
This name refers to His great authority and power.
萬君之又說代表的是一個權威和能力。
And it means He is sovereign over all the hosts of heaven.
祂有管理萬物,祂的主權。
But He is the one who has shut her womb.
但是祂也是那個令她不生育的神。
And she is seemingly cursed by Him.
似乎神是在這件事情上來救助她。
However, because she knows the Lord is sovereign,
her trials are going to drive her to Him.
但是因為她知道神是一個至高神,
她所經歷的只能夠推動祂來接近神。
She realizes the Lord is the only one who can help her.
她知道神是唯一能夠幫助她的神。
And in the midst of her trials,
she demonstrates tremendous trust in the Lord.
在哈娜所經歷的考驗中,
她能夠表達對神的極大的信心。
We see her trust in chapter 1, verses 9 through 28.
在聖母耳機上第一章9-28那裡,我們看見哈娜對神的信心。
And I'm going to try to summarize that part of the story for you.
雖然我剛才沒有讀,我們就盡量簡略地跟大家講一下。
As far as we know,
Hannah doesn't say anything to her rival, Penina.
據我們所知,哈娜並沒有跟比利娜講任何不好的說話。
She realizes there's a greater adversary than Penina.
因為她相信有一個攻擊她的極大的攻擊者。
In all of her trouble and testing, she controls her tongue.
在整個過程,在困難和考驗中,
她控制她的舌頭不說不應該的說話。
And she goes straight to God.
她直接來到神的面前。
The Bible says,
after they had eaten and drunk in Shiloh,
Hannah rose and went into the tabernacle.
在聖經這裡講到,
當他們吃完之後,喝完之後,
在侍羅那裡飲喝之後,
哈娜來到神的會幕之前,
Now Eli the priest was sitting on the seat
beside the doorpost of the temple of the Lord.
當時祭司以利坐在會幕前的柱子旁邊。
She was deeply distressed and prayed to the Lord
and wept bitterly.
當時哈娜非常痛苦,
在神的面前哭泣。
And she vowed a vow.
她對神做一個承諾。
And she said,
Oh Lord of hosts,
if you will indeed look on the affliction of your servant
and remember me.
在首次她就講到,
許個願,
耶和華,萬君之耶和華,
如果你垂聽僕女的苦情,
顧念不忘父女,
賜我一個兒子,
我就使他終生歸於耶和華。
And if you won't forget your servant,
but give me a son,
如果你能夠賜我一個兒子,
then I will give him to the Lord
all the days of his life,
我將他一生歸給你,
and no razor shall touch his head.
她不會用剃刀來剃他的頭。
These verses show us
that one day it was all too much
for Hannah to bear.
這裡我們看見,
在這一天裡面,
所有的事情對於哈娜來說
是實在忍受不住的。
And greatly grieved in heart,
she goes to the tabernacle
to pray to the Lord of hosts.
在一個極度傷痛的當中,
她來到神的面前來禱告。
She feels forgotten by God.
她覺得神是忘記了她了。
And she asks the Lord to remember her.
她求神來紀念她。
She promises the Lord
that if he will give her a son,
then she will give him to the Lord
all the days of his life.
如果神賜她一個兒子的話,
她願意將這個兒子歸給神,
一生來侍奉神。
She also promises that her son
will be a Nazarite for his life.
她答應神,
她的兒子要成為一個拿西爾人。
There are only three people in the Bible
who had a lifetime commitment to be a Nazarite.
在聖經裡面只有三個人物
是作為一個拿西爾人。
They are Samson, Samuel and John the Baptist.
他是參孫薩姆爾和施洗約翰。
This means he will eat nothing
produced by the grapevine.
作為一個拿西爾人的意義
就是他不會吃葡萄樹上所長的東西。
That means he will abstain
from the normal enjoyments of life
so he can serve the Lord.
意思就是說,
他會脫離一切一般人的享用
專心來侍奉神。
He will not go near a dead body.
他不會接近任何死的事物。
That means holier duties
will take precedence over the cares of this life.
意思就是說,
所有聖潔的侍奉
是比人裡面所有的經歷更加重要。
And also he will not cut his hair.
而且他不會剃頭。
Meaning he will be different from the world
and even from ordinary believers.
意思就是說,
他不會和一般人一樣。
This is a major commitment.
這是一個極端重要的遺身。
So then overcome with grief,
she continues to pray intensely before the Lord.
哈拿在極度憂傷的裡面
不斷地向神傾心吐怡。
And when Eli the priest sees her,
he thinks she is drunk and he reprimands her.
當以利見到這個婦人的時候,
他以為她是喝醉了酒,
而且來斥責她。
But she explains to him
that she is not drunk.
哈拿就向以利解釋說,
我不是喝醉。
She is deeply troubled,
pouring out her soul to the Lord.
極致地仇苦,來將自己向神傾心吐怡。
So Eli the priest then blesses her
and prays for her.
以利就在這個時候來祝福她,
為她來祈禱。
Then she leaves her burden there.
她就將她的重擔
在那個時候完全放下。
And she goes back to the meal with her family.
回去和他們家人一起享用那種飲宴。
The Bible says that her face was no longer downcast.
而且聖經裡面講到,
她念想已經不再帶任何的仇慾。
She had done more than release her psychological burden.
所以我們看見她不單止是放下
她心裡面那種的重擔。
She had prayed to the Lord
that He would remember her.
她是向神來祈禱,
神來紀念她。
And she had promised to honor God
with the blessing that He would give her.
所以她向神許了願,
求神來將她的福氣賜給她。
Also God's representative,
the priest, had blessed her and prayed for her.
而且代表神的祭司已經祝福她,
為她來禱告。
So the next morning,
Alcanna and his family
worship again in the tabernacle.
第二天,
伊利卡那在會幕那裡來敬拜神。
And then they return home.
完了之後,他們就回家了。
And after they return home,
God remembers Hannah.
當他們回到家的時候,
神紀念Hannah.
And she conceives,
and she bears a son.
神紀念她,
讓她能夠懷孕,
生了一個兒子。
She names him Samuel,
which means "Heard of the Lord".
薩姆爾這個名字,
就是說神已經聽了禱告。
Because she had asked the Lord for him,
and the Lord did not forget her.
因為Hannah向神祈求,
神並沒有忘記她。
One evidence of Hannah's trust
is her focus on the Lord.
其中一個證明Hannah的信心
就是因為她將她的注意力
集中在耶和華身上。
Three times in this passage,
it says Hannah was before the Lord.
在這段經文,
她三次提到說,
她在神的面前。
In 112,
she continued praying before the Lord.
在第一章第十二節那裡,
她不斷地在神的面前祈禱。
In 115,
she tells Eli the priest she was not drunk.
在第一章第十五節那裡,
她提到和以利說,
她不是喝醉酒,
而是將她在神的面前傾心圖義。
She is pouring out her soul before the Lord.
她將她所有的心思
向神傾倒出來。
In 119,
she and her family worship before the Lord.
在第一章第十九節那裡,
她在神的面前來敬拜。
For Hannah,
the Lord was the most real thing in her life.
對於Hannah來說,
神是最真實的一件事情。
There were probably other people
in the tabernacle when she prayed.
可能當她祈禱的時候,
有其他人同時在會幕那裡。
We know Eli the priest was there.
所以我們也知道
以利當時也在那裡。
But Hannah was only conscious
of the Lord's presence.
但是在眾人當中,
Hannah只能夠感覺神自己的同在。
The Lord was bigger and more real to her
than anything else in life.
神比任何事情更大和更重要。
She lived with the consciousness of God.
她活在神的意識當中。
And that is evidence of her focus on the Lord
and her trust in Him.
所以從此我們看到
Hannah的注意力就在神的身上。
Another evidence of her trust in the Lord
is how she keeps the vow that she made to the Lord.
另外一樣我們看到她的信心
就是她怎樣來還她的緣。
After Samuel was born,
it would have been easy for Hannah
to forget to keep her vow.
當她兒子撒姆爾出世的時候,
她很容易說
我忘記我自己對神的承諾。
She surely loved Samuel
and wanted to keep him for herself.
當然她會很愛這個撒姆爾,
想完全地擁有這個兒子。
But from the time of his birth,
she begins to prepare him
to fulfill this vow.
但是我們看到她從這個兒子出生,
她就開始準備怎樣來還這個緣。
She had made this vow to God.
她向神立下這個緣,
And now it must be fulfilled by Samuel.
但是她所立的緣
是需要她的兒子很自願地來還這個緣。
Elkanah, her husband,
will also have to cooperate
if she is going to be able to fulfill this vow.
她也需要伊麗嘉娜她的丈夫
來同意她還這個緣。
Because the child belongs to him too.
因為這個兒子
也同時是她的兒子。
So Hannah had to produce
or develop a spirit in Samuel.
所以我們看到Hannah
是需要在這個撒姆爾上
養成一種特別的自願性格。
So that he would be willing
to let her leave him at the tabernacle
to serve the Lord.
到有一天她能夠自願地
讓媽媽離開他
而自己留在這個會幕來侍奉神。
She has three years to do this
before he will be weaned.
所以有三年的時間
她才能夠斷奶。
For this reason
she doesn't go up to the feast
at the tabernacle
for the next three years.
所以因為這個原因
Hannah沒有跟著她的家族和丈夫
上去敬拜神。
Instead, she stays home with Samuel.
反而她留下來與撒姆爾一起。
And she spends every minute she has
in preparing him to leave her.
所以她用這個時候
每分每秒的時候
來準備他
這個兒子離開自己。
So Samuel is weaned at the age of three.
撒姆爾大概是三歲的時候就斷奶了。
And Hannah takes him to the tabernacle
and gives him into the hands
of Eli the priest.
所以斷奶之後
她帶著這個兒子
去到以利的面前
來將他獻給神。
She reminds Eli
that she is the woman
who is praying for a child
there in the tabernacle.
她會向這個以利提到
她就是那個婦人
在這個會幕裏面求一個兒子。
And God has answered her prayer.
神已經答應這個祈求。
Sorry, I lost my place for just a moment.
OK, here we go.
Since God gave Samuel to her,
she is now going to give him back to the Lord.
因為神將這個兒子給了她
她願意將這個兒子歸還給神。
And he will serve the Lord
as long as he lives.
她願意這個兒子一生來侍奉神。
She does this
knowing that now she will only be able
to see her son about one time a year.
她知道以後
她只能夠一年見她的兒子一次。
And that will be
when she comes to the tabernacle for the feast.
就是當她的家族去到會幕
來敬拜憲制義的時候。
從第二章裏面我們看到
會幕其實是一個很危險的地方。
其實是一個很危險
讓她將這個小孩留下。
因為以利的兒子是非常邪惡。
而且以利本身也不能夠
控制這兩個的兒子。
他們甚至是與一些婦人
在會幕事後的婦人來糾合。
她從這個被人帶上去聖殿
去到會幕憲制的祭物裏面
將那個來搶奪。
對於這個撒慕爾來說
那裏沒有一個基督教的學校。
那裏沒有一些青少年的士工
能夠栽培他。
哈娜是將這個所愛的兒子
所渴求的兒子
將他放在一個這樣的情況下。
這個不是一個很理想的情況。
可能哈娜就會很有藉口
來說我不願意將兒子
放在這樣的地方。
但是我們看到哈娜是
將她的注意力是集中在耶和華身上
而不是看到她周圍的環境。
她所做的是誰所答應神的。
她對神有一個很大的信心。
其實我們都應該將我們的兒女
獻給神。
因為他們是神給我們的禮物。
我不能夠完全地擁有我們的兒女。
我們是愚笨的
如果我們想完全地擁有他們。
但是如果我們做一個聰明的人的時候
我們會盡量在我們的兒女面前
來表示我們對神的信心。
希望他們以後會服侍神。
我們知道哈娜會做到這個。
因為我們看到
撒姆爾能夠專心來侍奉耶和華。
在聖經裡面講到
撒姆爾在神的面前侍奉耶和華。
他在神的面前來侍納。
他的注意力就在神耶和華的身上
就好像他母親一樣。
我們看到哈娜本身的考驗
和她對神的信心。
現在我們來看看哈娜本身的特性。
在第二章裡面提到哈娜的禱告
她說除了神之外沒有其他的。
她知道她的丈夫不能夠帶給她快樂。
她更加有智慧地知道
她的兒女不能夠帶給她完全的喜樂。
只有一位能夠完完全全帶給她完全的快樂。
就是主耶穌基督。
她知道只有神能夠滿足她的心。
在第二章裡面她這樣說:
她說:我的心因耶和華高舉
我的口向受敵來張開。
對不起,我漏了句。
因為我因為耶和華的救恩而歡樂。
只有耶和華為聖。
因為除他以外並有可比的。
也都是沒有一個盤石像我們的神。
哈娜勝過她的願望和她的懷疑。
她能夠勝過她的自憐。
她勝過她的自我中心和依靠自己。
她勝過所有沒有意義的事物,高傲和所有的惡勢力。
她能夠得勝因為她依靠耶和華。
她在極大的壓力之下能夠保持她的尊嚴和自制。
她並沒有因為傷害她的人而以牙還牙。
她的注意力就是集中在神給她要做的事。
她將所有的精力放在撒慕爾的身上,來準備她做侍奉耶和華的工作。
哈娜相信神完全是管理她的生命。
不單止是她所遇到的試煉和所有的考驗。
她知道一件事就是,她所遇到的事並不是一個錯誤。
所有發生在她身上的事,神都有一個目的在此。
可能所發生的事不是她願意所選擇的。
她相信她所經歷的所有情況是為了彰顯神的榮耀和他的國度,而且是為了讓她得到益處。
撒姆爾後來成為以色列一個很重要的屬靈領袖。
他是高納以色列頭兩個王,就是索羅和大衛。
他幫助以色列人脫離菲律斯人的壓迫。
他復甦了以色列的屬靈的光景。
但是神也是很豐足地祝福哈娜。
她是一個很敬虔的母親的模範。
她不是擁有所有的東西。
她有很多的考驗和失望。
但是在哈娜的生活上,我們能夠學到一個很重要的功課。
就是一個很敬虔的婦人會將她的心專注在耶和華,將所有的榮耀帶給她的神。
神是她生命中最重要的人物。
她的立志是要將她所學到的專注傳給她的兒女和周圍的人。
讓我們一起來祈禱。
天上的父神,我們感謝祢,因為祢是萬君的耶和華。
祢是完全掌管我們生命中任何的情況。
我祈求祢幫助我們怎樣在祢面前活著。
讓我們能夠不斷地在每一時每一刻體驗祢的同在和祢的愛。
當我們在試驗和危難當中的時候,讓我們專心地仰望祢。
幫助我們不去擔心其他人怎樣去想。
讓我們繼續能夠專心地忠於祢。
我們感謝祢給我們的母親。
我們感謝這裡會中所有的母親。
我們感謝他們在我們的家庭裡面,在我們的家庭裡面所付出的代價。
我們懇求祢將祢豐滿的恩典來賜給他們。
同主耶穌名給,阿們。